Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Advertising and Publicity Files, 1923, 1928-2004, 2009
  - Posters, 1953, 1978, 1982, 1984, 1986, 1987
    - What shall man live by? N.O.H., 1953 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      Golden rule poster traces "Love thy neighbor as thyself" across ten "living religions" over an image of President Norman O. Houston.
    - What shall man live by? H.O., 1953 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      Golden rule poster traces "Love thy neighbor as thyself" across ten "living religions" over an image of the Home Office.
    - Photo Highlights of the 1978 Las Vegas Leaders Roundtable Business Conference (Box 236, Folder 1)
      Materials include three black and white photo collage posters.
    - For C.L., 1982 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      This performance inspiration poster is dedicated to the spirit of San Diego District Manager C.L. Smith from Gilmer, Texas. The poster features a head shot of Smith hovering above a cowboy boot.
    - Founders Month '84, 1984 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      This poster features a black and white image of George A. Beavers, Jr., William Nickerson, Jr. and Norman O. Houston. The text underneath the title reads, "They sowed the seed, ours the job to reap the harvest." The text at the bottom of the poster reads, "On to Jamaica with Founders Month '84."
    - Help a Friend Start School Straight, 1986 September 6 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      This black and white poster for the Back to School with a Clear Head Rally at Jackie Robinson Stadium features an image of a hand reaching out to grab another that is extending upward from a pool of water.
    - Back to School with a Clear Head, 1986 September 6 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      This white poster with blue text is for a march and rally at Jackie Robinson Stadium. The graphics illustrate a scenic view of a winding road toward a school surrounded by nearby mountains, palm trees, clouds and birds. The slogan near the bottom of the poster reads, "Help a friend start school straight."
    - "A Salute to Minority Education" Dinner, 1987 May 27 (Box 236, Folder 1)
      This Golden State Minority Foundation poster is an invitation to attend a dinner with guest speaker and recipient of the Medal of Excellence, Christopher F. Edley, President and Chief Executive Officer of the United Negro College Fund. The poster features an image of six arms of various shades of red reaching upward.
  - Advertising files, circa 1945-1994
    - Negatives and illustration (Box 236, Folder 2)
      Materials include negatives of the GSM starburst logo, the exterior of the Home Office, the GSM mission statement and a Herald Examiner guide to Black History in Los Angeles which features the GSM Murals. Materials also include an illustration and negative of a modern matrix like design comprised of circles and sharp lines which GSM used for its Long Range Plan Network for the 80's Los Angeles Black Community. This design with the addition of copy and related graphs may also be found in box 240, folder 2.
    - Advertisements and annual reports binder, 1945-1962 (Box 237, Folder 1)
      Materials include advertisements for the Man with the Golden Pen, the mortgage loan service, the Home Office, life, sickness, accident and health insurance policies.
    - Letterhead and advertising press, 1954-1956 (Box 237, Folder 2)
      Materials include letterhead samples of GSM's award winning logo, a copy of Advertising Age in which a reader writes in about GSM's "Man with the Golden Pen" and advertisements in local publications.
    - Budgeterm insurance promotional materials, 1955 (Box 237, Folder 3)
      Materials include Budgeterm booklets, The Adventures of Goldie comic book, a training script, mailers and a script for a video.
    - Advertising specimens, circa 1960s (Box 237, Folder 4)
      Advertisements include GSM's New 7 Start Hospital and Surgical Plan, GSM's Security Master Series and The Man with the Golden Pen.
    - Ads binder, 1961 (Box 237, Folder 5)
      Advertisements include The Man with the Golden Pen, Important Notice of Dividend Declaration, Policies, "There is something new under the sun..." agent card, New and Revised Ordinary Portfolio, The Long Corridor...passageway to the chamber of life, Franklin D. Roosevelt United Nations Flag Day Prayer, Good News for the Whole Family: Introducing GSM's New Family Policy, Destination Tomorrow booklet, Faithful Protection: Budgeterm Insurance, Inside GSM, Annual Reports to Policyowners and an Independent Comparative Report leaflet.
    - "House" proof sheet, 1994 June 28 (Box 237, Folder 6)
      Proof sheet includes images of a house used for advertising.
    - "A New Way" training program binder, circa 1980s (Box 238, Folder 1-4)
      Materials include training script, description and layout for visuals. This binder is divided into the following sections: Marketing strategy, product understanding, product knowledge, prospecting, sales presentations, underwriting, policy delivery, policy service, conservation and what can be achieved.
    - Founders photographs, negatives and layouts (Box 239, Folder 1)
      Materials include mounted Founder's Month photo, negative and advertisement layouts as well as mounted photographs of George A. Beavers, Jr. and executives such as Ernest Shell, Ivan J. Houston and Verna A. Hickman at a Board room presentation.
    - Mounted photographs, circa 1960s (Box 239, Folder 2)
      Two mounted photographs used for advertisements include one of a family in front of their house and another of the boy sitting on the train tracks from the Destination Tomorrow campaign.
    - Illustrations and paste-ups (Box 239, Folder 3)
      Illustrations and paste-up advertising boards for The Golden Pen GSM 50, hospitalization policies, sickness and accident policies, Homecoming 1975, Home Office, GSM Today, Mother's Day and a cookbook.
    - Mural booklet copy and paste-ups, circa 1949 (Box 240, Folder 1)
      Materials include copy, oversize mural images on cardboard and paste-up boards for booklet on GSM's "The Negro in California History" murals. This folder also includes a paste-up board for "GSM In Our Community: Generation after Generation" advertisement.
    - Illustrations and paste-ups, circa 1979 (Box 240, Folder 2)
      Materials include illustrations and paste-up boards for GSM's Long Range Plan Network for the 80's Los Angeles Black Community and the following illustrations: a jockey riding a horse, Steamboat on Bay and musician Quincy Jones.
    - Advertising plan, illustrations and paste-ups (Box 240, Folder 3)
      Materials include "A Total P.R., Advertising and Public Service Program for GSM" illustrated poster, Stretch Your Program and Community Relations brochures paste-up boards, Family Group illustration and "Golden State Broadens Its Market" paste-up board.
    - Home Office photographs, illustrations and paste-ups, circa 1949 (Box 240, Folder 4)
      Home Office photographs, proof sheets and an illustration of the building's exterior affixed to a paste-up board.
    - Illustrations, logos and paste-ups, circa 1980s (Box 241, Folder 1)
      Materials include GSM marching band illustration, Medal of Excellence illustration and the following paste-up boards: Have it All and Get Something Back, the GSM Afro-American Art Collection, Black Insurance Pioneers, Memorial Funeral Service, Community Service Award Program, Partners in Progress, Crenshaw Neighborhood Housing Services, Calendar and the GSM starburst logo.
    - GSM Service Anniversaries paste-ups, 1987-1988 (Box 241, Folder 2)
      Paste-up boards for Golden State Mutual Service Anniversaries include employee names, years of service, awards, professional designations, promotions, transfers, employees of the month and a bulletin board with dates for Sunday Gospel Hour, Founder's Month, 64th Anniversary of GSM, 40th Anniversary of Home Office, Company Picnic and Search for the Great Pumpkin.
    - Logos, copy and typefaces, circa 1980s (Box 242, Folder 1)
      Materials include Into the 80's presentation plate, The Golden Voice copy, letterhead and envelope samples, Development of the Long Range Plan plate, typeface samples and starburst logo transfer decals.
    - Illustrations, negatives and paste-ups, circa 1980s (Box 242, Folder 2)
      Materials include Home Office exterior illustrations, negatives and paste-up boards, 60 birthday candle illustration paste-up board, General Agent Recruiting Ad paste-up and prints and A Sales Career with Golden State Mutual paste-up board.
    - Illustrations, negatives and paste-ups (Box 242, Folder 3)
      Materials include the following illustrations: "Spotlight," Medal of Excellence, dove, boxing gloves, agent, Merry Christmas, Happy New Year, Education and illustrated paste-up boards of an agent, the state of California and food found in the Golden State.
    - Negatives and logos, circa 1980s (Box 243, Folder 1)
      Materials include Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company Home Office: Adams and Western, Los Angeles logo plate and negatives of the following: GSM logos, 60 Year Anniversary, Agent of the Month, Adopt a School Program, doves, Oakland District Office History, A New Way, GSM Afro-American Art Collection, Need a Silent Partner? and Golden State Minority Foundation.
    - Paste-ups and negatives, circa 1980s (Box 243, Folder 2)
      Materials include paste-up boards for GSM's Insurance and Savings Plans and negatives for the following: The Man with the Golden Pen logo, dove, United States at a glance map and About Jamaica.
    - Illustrations and paste-ups (Box 244, Folder 1)
      Materials include illustrations of a first place trophy, fish, lobster, turkey, Living Beauty, gangster advertiser, families, family services, academic programs, paid child car, father and daughter, people's faces, Yoshida, Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., college, female student, parrot, conservation, collecting your debit, GSM agents and a telephone by Charles Paige. Paste-ups include the following: Destination Tomorrow, Shoes Wear Out, Funerals Cost, 65, Your First Step, Service is Our Business, California, Postal Box, Spotlight, Outstate, Are You Ready for Success?, Returning Money to the Black Community and two files of marketing strategy symbols and "New Strategy" illustrations by Charles Paige.
    - Illustrated paste-ups (Box 244, Folder 2)
      Paste-up boards illustrated by Charles Paige include the following images: Drug and alcohol prevention, counselor, ethnic legal service, legal resources and legislation or lobby information. Additional paste-up boards include images of the following: mountains, museum, How Can We Better Serve, group of people, women, salesman, insurance protection, man and woman embracing, man with lamb, training and development of Black individuals, map of the United States and a bearded man with a crown of thorns. New Way Art illustrations include a dove, piggy bank, a cross with a sign that reads Peace, a meeting with a flip chart, Are you ready for this?, Protect Your Interest in Times of Sorrow and doves flying toward the sun.
    - Copy and paste-ups, circa 1950s and 1960s (Box 245, Folder 1)
      Benefits and plans copy and paste-up boards for advertisements concerning Children's Insurance and Savings Plans.
    - Promotional placards (Box 245, Folder 2)
      Materials include the following two placards: Burial Insurance and The Benevolence Plan.
    - Contact information proofs (Box 245, Folder 3)
      Materials include contact information proof sheets for GSM Directors, Officers and Field Managers.
    - "A New Way" illustrations, negatives and slides, circa 1980s (Box 245, Folder 4)
      Materials include "A New Way" training program negatives, slides and illustrations by William E. Pajaud.
    - Advertisements, circa 1960s, 1980s (Box 245, Folder 5)
      Materials include advertisements for Family Policy, the Man with the Golden Pen, Familife Policy, Hospital Plan and Win $100.
    - Copy and paste-ups, circa 1960s (Box 246, Folder 1)
      Materials include copy and illustrated paste-up boards for Last Expense Fund, Retirement Fund, Disability, Education Fund, Emergency Fund, Security-Master, Savings Plan and the Housewife's Insurance and Savings Plan. Materials also include tables for income, monthly and annual premiums.
    - Proofs and paste-ups, circa 1965 (Box 246, Folder 2)
      Materials include paste-up boards for Woman's Original Security Program, Income Protection and Hospital Plan, Children's Insurance, Last Expense Fund, Mortgage or Rent Fund, Emergency Fund, Education Fund, Guaranteed Monthly Income, Retirement Income, Disability Income and Housewife's Insurance and Savings Plan. Materials include proofs for the following: Woman's Original Security Program, Income Protection and Hospital Plan, Children's Insurance and Savings Plans, Security-Master, $10,000 Insurance and Savings Plan, $25,000 Insurance and Savings Plan and Sickness, Accident, Hospital and Surgical Policies.
    - Contact sheets and negatives, 1977-1979 (Box 246, Folder 3)
      Advertising materials include photographic contact sheets and negatives for the Leaders Roundtable in New Orleans, fishing trip, Management Board work shop, Home Office, Home Office personnel and All Year Awards breakfasts in Detroit and North Texas.
  - Audiovisual materials, circa 1960s-2004
    - Slides, circa 1960s, 1971, 1973-1982, 1985, 1987 (Box 247, Box 248, Box 249, Box 250, Box 251, Box 252, Box 253, Box 254, Box 255, Box 256, Box 257, Box 258, Box 259)
      Box 247-248: Two sets of "GSM Presents..." glass slides that tell an illustrated full color story of a family taken care of by Golden State Mutual insurance. (1960s)
      Box 249: Slides include images of advertisements, symbols, logos, story pages, credit frames, Security Master Series, Los Angeles aerial view, United States map, homes, hands with golden pens, Founders, Board of Directors, Helen E. Batiste, clerical staff, historical mural research, Mabel Cleveland, A.J. Williams, Ivan J. Houston, William E. Pajaud, Norman O. Houston, Bertha Nickerson, Norman B. Houston, Verna A. Hickman, Edgar J. Johnson, George A. Beavers, Jr., Home Office exterior and interior, Home Office cafeteria, Leonard Grimes, Home Office printing press, Westside agents, Eastside agents, Compton agents, 50th Anniversary cake and I Am Somebody cake. (1960s, 1973-1978)
      Box 250: Slides include images of Home Office Grapevine, Las Vegas Leaders Roundtable, Founders Month, Vancouver Leaders Roundtable and Acapulco Leaders Roundtable. (1969-1971)
      Box 251: Slides include images of advertisements, actors, collection forms, financial reports, GSM Foundation Board of Directors and Los Angeles Urban League. (circa 1970s, 1978-1980, 1982)
      Box 252: Slides include images of advertisements, proof of death forms and funeral homes. (1979, 1982)
      Box 253: Slides include images of advertisements, pen and ink illustrations, watercolor illustrations, agents, home visits, forms, policies and housewives. (1979-1980)
      Box 254: Slides include images of advertisements, agents, families, funeral and burial expenses forms, agent presentations, joggers, house visits, Mahalia Jackson church fans, Peace of Mind and Security GSM mail holders, fishing trip, Los Angeles Urban League and agent's appointment book. (1979-1980)
      Box 255: Slides include images of advertisements, agents, policyowners, families, Africa, African art from the Museum of Primitive Art, African American art and illustrations of slavery. (1979-1980)
      Box 256: Slides include images of organizational charts, You and GSM publication, Golden State Into the '80s publication, "A New Way" presentation, Memorial Service Life Insurance Policy advertisements, Memorial Service Life Insurance logo, "A New Way" binders, Cash Burial Insurance Policy brochures, Can You Afford to Die? advertisement, Eliminate the Worry of Funeral and Burial Expenses advertisement, "A New Way" flip chart presentation, Los Angeles Urban League, marketing strategy symbols and illustrations by Charles Paige. (1980)
      Box 257: Slides include images of advertisements, agents, home visits, policyowners and life insurance applications. (1980)
      Box 258: Slides include images of advertisements, agents, "A New Way" flip charts, Holy Cross Cemetery, Home Office building exterior, policyowners, Richard Wyatt's Insurance Man mural restoration and Golden State Minority Foundation Salute to Minority Education poster. (1980, 1985, 1987)
      Box 259: Materials include overhead projector slides for business insurance seminar.
    - Phonograph records, 1938, 1951, 1952, 1956, 1957 (Box 260)
      Twenty-two phonograph records include the following titles: Golden State Life Insurance Broadcast, Confirming the Honorary LL.D. Degree on Norman O. Houston with Dr. Mary McLeod Bethune, Life Insurance Service: A Special Message to the Agency Force of GSMLIC by President Norman O. Houston, Radio WMAQ "Jack Eigen's Chez Show," GSM Presents "Man With Golden Pen" and Golden State Mutual Expanding Markets - Expanding Needs. Materials also include the following business insurance seminar 33 1/3 LPs: The Light Way & Tune In to Turn On, A Stockholder Dies, The Turning Point, Partners and Looking Back.
    - 35 mm film, undated (Box 261)
      Eleven canisters of 35 mm film include the following titles: GSM Contest, The Turning Point, The Light Way & Tune In to Turn On, Looking Back, A Stockholder Dies, Partners, Ain't No Ammo Peiping and Making Sales with You'll Earn a Fortune.
    - Compact cassettes, 1975, 2004 (Box 262)
      Thirty audiocassettes include the following titles: Hall of Honor Dedication by George A. Beavers, Jr., Oakland District Office interview, For the Record pilot, Mr. W.P. Mosley, Golden State Mutual 5-60 second spots, Walter E. Freeman, Golden State Mutual Greeting, L.A. East groundbreaking, Recycling Black Dollars, Golden State Mutual, Pierce/Neighborhood Education, Dixieland, Walter E. Freeman's My Message Home Office of GSM and New Orleans Jazz.
    - Mini data cartridge tapes, undated (Box 262)
      Materials include three unlabeled mini data cartridge tapes.
    - DVDs, undated (Box 263)
      Nine DVDs include the following titles: GSM Commercial, Golden State Mutual Life Commercial Campaign, Operation Hope: Banking on Our Future, Television Reel and Radio Reel.
    - Compact Discs, undated, 2002 (Box 263)
      Five CDs include the following titles: Golden State Mutual Life Benevolence Plan 60 sec. commercial, Golden State Mutual Banner and GSM Press Kit.
    - Videocassettes, 1993, undated (Box 263)
      Materials include three VHS tapes, two Betamax tapes and one U-Matic tape. The U-Matic tape is a GSM and You dupe master, the Betamax tapes include Golden State Mutual Life edited master and duplication master and the VHS tape titles include the following: Golden State Mutual Foundation Presentation, Golden State Mutual P.S.A. and Soul Beat T.V. commercial.
    - Floppy disks, undated (Box 263)
      Materials include three floppy disks. One of the disks is labeled GSM Express Logo jpg.
- Historical Murals and Afro-American Art Collection Files, 1948-2000
  The GSM Afro-American Art Collection began when the murals depicting the Negro's contribution to the growth and development of California, were first installed on the walls of the Home Office lobby in 1949. The murals were followed the next year by Richmond Barthe's bronze bust of Founder William Nickerson, Jr., which was commissioned and paid for by GSM employees. Mural and Collection brochures were printed for distribution to groups and individuals who came to the building for a tour.
  Materials include files related to the GSM Historical Murals and Afro-American Art Collection.
  - Historical Murals files, 1947-1949
    Artists Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston were commissioned in 1948 to paint the murals portraying the history of the Negro in California for Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company's Home Office on Adams Boulevard at Western Avenue in Los Angeles, California. The research that forms the basis of selection of the mural subjects was done by librarian Miriam Matthews and historian Titus Alexander. Woodruff and Alston traveled to California in August of 1948 for a research tour wherein they visited historical sites, examined records in libraries and museums, and filled sketchbooks with drawings of native rocks, flowers, terrain, costumes, art and equipment. Following the tour, a conference was held with the researchers and company officials to select the mural subjects. Each artist chose the period he would portray in his panel. Mr. Alston selected "exploration and colonization" and Mr. Woodruff, "settlement and development." The artists worked closely with Architect Paul R. Williams to have the color and style of the murals in harmony with the architecture and decorative design of the building. The murals, unveiled during the opening week ceremonies for GSM's new Home Office on August 19, 1949, cover two panels, 16' 5" by 9' 3 1/4" and hang on opposite walls of the building's lobby. Father H. Randolph Moore delivered the invocation for the mural unveiling ceremony and Titus Alexander served as Master of Ceremonies. Mrs. Charlotta Bass, publisher of the California Eagle, pulled the cord to unveil the Charles Alston mural and Mrs. Gussie Woods, mother of Hale Woodruff, pulled the cord to unveil the Woodruff mural.
    Materials include source files on the murals, transcripts from an Executive Committee Conference with the mural artists, correspondence with the artists and architect Paul R. Williams, public relations materials such as press releases, informational booklets and press clippings, correspondence concerning the involvement of librarian Miriam Matthews and historian Titus Alexander in the historical research project, a folder of suggested mural subjects, photographs of the artists' Mural Research Tour, pre-installation and unveiling photos, a folder on the route of the Mural Research Tour in California which includes an itinerary and descriptions for points of interest, a Mural Research Tour report that includes correspondence with the artists and transcriptions of telephone conversations between the artists and GSM Chairman of the Board George A. Beavers, Jr.
    - Mural research photographs, 1948 (Box 264, Folder 1)
      Photographs include images of conferences with Miriam Matthews, Titus Alexander, Charles Alston, Hale Woodruff, George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston, Paul R. Williams and Verna Hickman and of artists Alston and Woodruff with GSM photographer and commercial artist Leonard Grimes on the murals research tour.
    - Murals pre-installation photographs, 1948 (Box 264, Folder 2)
      Photographs include images of conferences with Hale Woodruff, Charles Alston, Miriam Matthews, Titus Alexander, Verna Hickman, George A. Beavers, Jr., Norman O. Houston and Edgar Johnson, Alston and Woodruff's murals research tour and Beavers, Batiste, Houston and Williams unwrapping the murals prior to installation.
    - Murals source files, 1948 (Box 264, Folder 3-5)
      Materials include a Murals on California History press release, transcripts of conference with mural artists, correspondence between Verna Hickman and Hale Woodruff, Charles Alston, Miriam Matthews and Titus Alexander, clippings, resumes for Matthews, Alexander, Alston and Woodruff and transcripts for research conferences with Alexander and Hickman.
    - Mural artists conference notes and research, 1948-1949 (Box 264, Folder 6)